So you only really
need one thing to
stand out on YouTube
and to bring viewers
back and to turn
them into buyers. So
in this video, I'm
going to show what
it is, the big
problem we all face
that stops us getting
it right. And then
I'm going to walk
you through a step
-by -step system to
position your channel, your
marketing and your offer,
so you can build
a hulk of a
system that does the
heavy lifting for you.
All right, so let's
start with the big
problem this solves. So
imagine you're in the
finance niche and you
want to grow a
channel teaching basic kind
of investment tips. But
this is your competition.
You've got Mark Tilbury,
multi -millionaire, niche, professional
accountant, Dave Ramsey, household
name, millions of followers.
And you, you've got
$200 ,000 saved up.
Why would anyone watch
your tiny channel when
they could click on
one of them who's
achieved way more? Well,
the truth is, if
you try to go
head -to -head, you're
going to lose. And
that's exactly what we
don't want. So instead,
we use the David
versus Goliath strategy. Because
David, he didn't beat
Goliath by playing the
same game. He used
an advantage that only
he had. And that's
what we're going to
get you to do
too. Except... Except your
advantage isn't a deadly
rock. It's your backstory.
Your backstory is the
only thing your competition
can't copy. It's what
makes you relatable, credible,
and most importantly, different
and unique. Harnessing a
backstory is what gets
results on YouTube, even
when others have more
views, more money, and
more fame. But surely
a story can't be
that powerful. Well, let
me show you why
this is such a
powerful tool. So remember
at the start of
this course, I made
you listen to my
backstory. About how I
went from getting laughed
at, having no views,
to being the guy
who these big... YouTube
channels started asking for
advice. And then I
quit that channel and
I started again. I
launched the software and
I found an even
better way to grow.
And then I ended
up getting a ton
of success from it.
Every single second of
that story was intentional.
It built credibility by
showing you that I've
done the reps and
I've got the result
that you hopefully want
to. It makes me
relatable because you probably
felt the same pain
that I spoke about
in it. So you're
going, this guy gets
me. And it makes
my system feel way
more unique because it's
just not another recycled...
YouTube tactic. It's something
I discovered for myself.
So your backstory isn't
just a differentiator. It's
your channel, your product,
and your marketing. And
when your viewers see
that you had the
problem they have found
a solution and built
a system to solve
it, they trust you,
they believe in your
message, and they start
to see you as
someone who truly gets
it. So this is
why we position your
channel and your business
around your backstory. It
is your David versus
Goliath unfair advantage. So
now I'm going to
show you how to
position your entire channel
and your business and
your marketing around your
backstory... In a way
that's not just about
you. In a way
that you can still
talk about a ton
of different things, even
though your viewers are
going to feel like
you're the expert on
just one topic. And
to do that, we're
going to follow a
really simple three step
framework. First, what you
need to do is
answer these two questions.
Firstly, what's the problem
you had that your
ideal viewers have now?
And then secondly, what's
the result you got
your ideal viewers want
to? So let's use
Meadow as an example.
Her problem was she
was in a toxic
relationship with a narcissist
that wrecked her confidence
and her result was
she learned how to
spot narcissists and escape
those relationships. So now
she helps others do
the same thing. That's
the foundation of her
entire channel and her
business. And if you're
thinking, but I'm a
doctor, I've never had
back pain, the thing
I teach people to
get rid of myself.
That's OK, because we're
going to borrow the
backstory of your ideal
clients instead. So you
just need a real
problem and a real
transformation based on how
you've helped others. So
that might be their
problem is they have
back pain. And the
result you got someone
else was your new
system that fixes backs
in a split second.
So once you've nailed
the problem result, the
next step is to
get super specific about
who you're helping and
the easiest way to
do this. So just
think about who you
were before you figured
all of this out.
So that version of
you is your avatar
that you're going to
try and appeal to.
And then all you
do is you fill
out this simple list.
So you write their
age and we need
to make sure the
age isn't 18 to
60. That just won't
work. Pick an age
group. The sex, sorry,
sex, the location, if
it matters where they
are in the world.
We don't need to
go too granular. I
just put English speaking
countries. Then we want
to think about the
type of person they
are. So this could
be a job title,
a life role or
a lifestyle label like
a new dad or
a corporate dropout or
a solo founder. And
then we just want
to work out the
top three problems they
think they have that
stop them getting the
result they want. Now,
this is where you
got to be careful,
because these problems might
not be the real
cause of their issue,
because people often don't
know why they have
a problem and they
tend to blame everything
other than the real
reason for it. So
you need to list
what they think their
top three problems that
are stopping them getting
a result are not
what they actually are.
So let's use Meadow
as an example again.
She targeted women, probably
25 to 45 years
old, let's say. The
type of person could
be ambitious, but recovering,
who are dating. Or
stuck in toxic relationships.
The audience perceived problems
might be I keep
attracting the wrong man.
I can't trust myself.
I don't know how
to spot red flags.
OK, so now that
you've clarified the problem,
the result and exactly
who you're helping, it's
time to turn it
into a simple statement
that guides everything you
do on YouTube and
in your business. And
the formula is this.
I help achieve result
by solving the core
problem. That's it. So
Meadow's statement could be
I help women spot,
survive and heal from
narcissistic relationships. Or a
business focused statement. If
you're a channel about
growing businesses, it could
be something like I
help business owners generate
sales views and leads
using YouTube, which is
my statement. Or if
you're a fitness channel,
it could be I
help busy dads get
strong and lean using
short 20 minute workouts
with no gym required.
And then everything you
make your videos and
you offer your copy
about can now be
positioned as the solution
to this problem for
that person. Now, if
you like, you can
whack that statement in
your YouTube band like
I did. You don't
actually have to share
this with anyone. It's
more there so that
you never make anything
that isn't positioned to
solve this problem for
that person. Because if
you start doing that,
you can't become known
for one thing. Now,
the thing that everyone
hates about this is
they go, Ed, I
don't want to talk
about the same thing
over and over again.
But that's how this
works. Because imagine you're
selling umbrellas. People don't
buy an umbrella because
it's carbon fibre or
because it folds neatly.
They buy it for
one big reason. They
want to stay dry
in the rain. I
call your positioning statement
the top of your
umbrella, the one big
problem you solve for
your ideal customers. But
under that umbrella, you
can still talk about
anything size, weight, style,
durability, handle, colour, as
long as each of
those things ties back
to the main goal,
which is staying dry.
So, for example, if
my umbrella statement is
I help business owners
generate sales, views and
leads using YouTube. This
means I can still
make videos about storytelling,
editing, intros, productivity, mindset,
offers, email, automation. As
long as each video
is packaged with a
thumbnail and title that
serves the problem, I've
decided to position myself
as the expert on,
which is why this
video here about editing
is positioned as blowing
up your business. If
I'd called it how
I edit faster in
Final Cut Pro with
no connection to sales,
business or audience growth,
my viewers aren't coming
back to me. And
new viewers would look
at the rest of
my channel and go,
hang on, this guy
never talks about Final
Cut. I'm not going
to watch anything else.
So views drop off,
sales slow down. The
whole entire system falls
apart because I am
not a channel about
editing. I'm a channel
about generating sales, views
and leads. So remember
this. You can talk
about anything as long
as you frame it
as the solution to
the core problem your
viewers want solved. That
is the power of
the umbrella strategy and
positioning. So now let's
build your statement. I
want you to start
by answering these two
questions. What's the problem
you had that your
audience has now? What's
the result you got
that your audience wants
to? Which is basically
your backstory. And then
use this structure to
help you position. I
help X type of
person do transformation or
do the same thing.
So here's an example.
If you have a
qualification in something, so
you're a doctor or
a physio or you
have client results, you
then do the same
thing. But you say,
what's the one big
problem they have and
the result they want
that I have a
ton of experience getting
them? OK, so now
you've got that. Go
over to the custom
AI and click on
the positioning bot here
and just type in
your positioning statement and
say, give me feedback.
And what it's going
to do is it's
going to help you
refine it. Now, you
might not need to
refine it at all,
but it's going to
give you some feedback,
some suggestions, and then
it's going to say,
here's some rough kind
of titles you could
make around this positioning
statement. Now, don't go
and use these titles.
It's just to give
you some inspiration. But
I'd have a bit
of back and forth
chatter with this and
it will do an
amazing job of helping
you get clarity here.
Now, something important to
note here. If you
are newer or a
small channel, this positioning
is your minimum viable
positioning. Remembering our fail
as fast as you
can system. So it
won't be right. Over
time, as we get
data and we post
stuff and we see
what happens, we will
optimise it. With that
data. So it might
slightly change over time.
What you need to
understand is you don't
want to get paralysed
by fear of what
if it's wrong, it's
probably going to be
if you're new to
this. But we have
to start somewhere. And
the next video is
going to help you
uncover that and ask,
do we need to
fix anything that's potentially
blocking your results?